Neugass, Fritz; Papers ger007
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
- Theater and Film, 1950s-1970s; 6; 32 file folders
  - Disney's nature films and nature photographers, Undated (Box 19 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 34)
    Typescripts (4), notes, photographs (49), publicity, clippings.
  - "Funny Face", Film with Audrey Hepburn and Fred Astaire and fashion photography by Richard Avedon, Undated (Box 19 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 35)
  - German Theater (Deutsches Theater) in New York, Undated (Box 19 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 36)
    Typescript, programs, clippings.
  - Hansel and Gretel, puppet show, Undated (Box 19 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 37)
    Typescript, photograph, publicity, program.
  - Hochhuth, Rolf. "The Deputy" ("Der Stellvertreter") in New York, Undated; typescript, clippings (Box 19 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 38)
  - International and American films, Undated (Box 19 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 39)
    Typescripts (5), photographs (7).
  - "Jonas". German psychoanalytical film, Undated (Box 19 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 40)
    Typescript, photographs (16).
  - Madol, Hans Roger, Undated; typescript, clippings (Box 19 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 41)
  - "My Fair Lady" (play), Undated (Box 19 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 42)
    Typescripts (2), photographs (6), playbill, clippings.
  - "The Naked Eye", film on photography, Undated (Box 20 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 1)
  - Negroes in the American Theater, Undated (Box 20 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 2)
    Typescript, notes, photographs (43), publicity, programs, clippings.
  - New York Film Festival, 1968-1969 (Box 20 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 3)
  - New York Film Festival (8th), 1970 (Box 20 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 4)
  - New York Film Festival (9th), 1971; typescript (Box 20 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 5)
  - New York Film Festival (13th), 1975 (Box 20 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 6)
  - New York Film Festival (14th), 1976 (Box 20 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 7)
    Typescript, photographs (6), publicity.
  - New York Film Festival (15th), 1977 (Box 20 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 8)
  - Oenslager, Donald. Scenic design collection from 4 centuries, with catalog, Undated (Box 20 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 9)
    Typescript, notes, photograph, publicity.
  - Richter, Hans. Chess film and "Dreams that Money can Buy", including autograph letter of the artist, 1954 (Box 20 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 10)
    Some handwritten picture inscriptions. Typescript, photographs (16), publicity, clippings.
  - Shakespeare in the US, Undated (Box 20 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 11)
  - Special effects in film, Undated (Box 20 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 12)
    Typescript, notes, photographs (25).
  - Stage and Screen Reviews. Theater in New York, Season 1961/1962 and 1962/1963, articles on individual New York performances, Undated (Box 20 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 13)
    Typescripts (9), clippings.
  - Stage Design after 1945. Exhibit in Zurich, 1964 (Box 20 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 14)
  - Stunts in Film, "On the Waterfront", Undated (Box 20 (6-Theater and Film), Folder 15)
    Typescript, photographs (4), publicity.
- Photography and Photographers, 1950s-1979; 7; 77 file folders
  This series consists of typescripts by Neugass, photographs and clippings on contemporary photographers and photography exhibits as well as photographic methods and mediums.
  - Abstract photography, Undated (Box 20 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 16)
    Typescripts (3), notes, correspondence, photographs (17), publicity, clippings.
  - Aerial photograpy, pictures taken from the air, Undated (Box 20 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 17)
    Typescripts (2), photographs (13), clippings.
  - American Photography, Undated (Box 20 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 18)
    Typescripts (11), photographs (4).
    See also Box 25, Folder 16.
  - American Society of Magazine Photographers, Undated (Box 20 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 19)
  - Atget, Eugene, Undated (Box 20 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 20)
  - Avedon, Richard, 1947-1977; photographs (Box 20 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 21)
    See also Box 25, Folder 17.
    Exhibit Metropolitan Museum, 1978. Typescript, notes, photographs (11), publicity, clippings.
  - Biasi, Mario de, Undated (Box 20 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 22)
    Typescripts (3), photographs (48), clippings.
  - Bite of a rattlesnake, filming of, Undated (Box 20 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 23)
    Typescript, photographs (10).
  - The Bitter Years, American Photography in the 1930s, Undated (Box 20 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 24)
    Typescript, photographs (2).
  - Book reviews, books and annuals of photography, Undated (Box 20 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 25)
    Typescripts (12).
  - Bourke-White, Margaret, Undated (Box 20 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 26)
  - Brady, Mathew B., Photography in the American Civil War, Undated (Box 20 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 27)
    Typescripts (2), photographs (15), publicity, clippings.
  - Brandt, Bill. Exhibit in Museum of Modern Art, 1960 (Box 20 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 28)
    No text by Fritz Neugass. Photographs (11), publicity, clippings.
  - Brassai. Exhibit of his graffiti photography in Museum of Modern Art, 1957 (Box 20 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 29)
  - Capa, Robert, Undated (Box 20 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 30)
  - Cartier-Bresson, Henri, Undated (Box 20 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 31)
    Typescripts (3), photographs (6), publicity, clippings.
    See also Box 25, Folder 18.
  - Color Photography, Undated (Box 20 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 32)
  - Concerned Photographer, Undated (Box 20 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 33)
  - Eastman, George, and the Eastman House in Rochester, Undated (Box 20 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 34)
    Typescript, photographs (51), clippings.
  - Eisenstaedt, Alfred, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 1)
  - Elisofon, Eliot. Photography of Indian Temples, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 2)
  - European "Tops" Amateur Photography. Exhibited in New York, 1952 (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 3)
    Including correspondence, picture inscriptions, no text. Photographs (32), clippings.
  - Flash Close-ups, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 4)
    Typescript, photographs (16), publicity.
  - French Photography, Modern, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 5)
  - Haas, Ernst, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 6)
  - Henle, Fritz, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 7)
    Typescripts (2), photographs (6).
  - Historical Photography, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 8)
    Typescripts (8), photographs (20), publicity, clippings.
  - Individual Photographers. Articles, mostly on American photographers, including Cecil Beaton, Leonard McCombe, Barbara Morgan, Ylla, Suzanne Szazs, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 9)
    Typescripts (12), photographs (7), publicity.
  - Industrial Photography in the US, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 10)
    Typescripts (2), photographs (54), clippings.
    See also Box 25, Folder 19.
  - IPEX, International Photo Exhibition, Washington, 1957 (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 11)
    Including text in English, also printed articles of 1965, with pseudonym Friedrich Brentano for Fritz Neugass. Typescripts (4), photographs (37), clippings.
  - Jacobi, Lotte. Including 5 autograph letters by Jacobi, 1964-1965 (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 12)
  - Japan. Photography in Japan today, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 13)
    Typescripts (4), photographs (25), clippings.
    See also Box 25, Folder 20.
  - Karsh, Yousuf, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 14)
  - Kolibri / Hummingbirds. Including, picture inscriptions, printed text by Fritz Neugass, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 15)
    Photographs (2), clippings.
  - Läubli, Walter. Photographer of Zurich, editor of The Camera, contains 48 original photos and 2 color transparencies by Läubli, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 16)
    See also Box 25, Folder 21.
  - Landscape Photography in the US. Exhibit in Museum of Modern Art, 1963 (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 17)
  - Lange, Dorothea, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 18)
  - Laposky, Ben F., Electronic Abstractions. Including 2 letters by Laposky, publicity, clippings, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 19)
  - Larsen, Lisa, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 20)
    See also Box 25, Folder 22.
  - Liberman, Alexander. Portraits of Artists, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 21)
  - Life Contest for Young Photographers, 1951 (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 22)
  - Metropolitan Museum, New York, Photo Collections, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 23)
    Typescript, photographs (13), publicity.
  - Metropolitan Museum. Yearly exhibits "Photography in the Fine Arts", Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 24)
    Typescripts (5), photographs (29), catalogs, clippings.
  - Modern cameras and techniques, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 25)
    Typescripts (6), photographs (6), publicity, clippings.
  - Movement in Art and Photography, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 26)
    Typescript, photograph, clipping.
  - Museum of Modern Art, Photo - Exhibits, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 27)
    Typescripts (9), photographs (92), publicity.
    See also Box 25, Folder 23.
  - Museums for Photography, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 28)
  - Newman, Arnold, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 29)
  - Photo League, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 30)
  - Photography, Painting, Sculpture, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 31)
    Typescripts (2), photographs (3), including 1 photo by Fritz Neugass.
  - Portrait in Art and Photography, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 32)
    Typescripts (2), photographs (9), clipping.
  - 100 Years of Portrait Photography, Exhibit Brooklyn Museum, 1951 (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 33)
    Typescripts (2), photographs (8), publicity, clippings.
  - Russian Photography, Exhibit in the US, 1970 (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 34)
    No text by Fritz Neugass, photographs (13), publicity, clippings.
  - Siskind, Aaron. Including 2 autograph letters of the photographer, 1954 (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 35)
  - Smith, W. Eugene, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 36)
  - Space and Weather Photography, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 37)
    Typescripts (5), photographs (26), publicity, clippings.
  - Steichen, Edward, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 38)
    Typescripts (8), photographs (49), catalog, publicity, clippings.
  - Steichen, Edward. Family of Man exhibit in Museum of Modern Art, 1964 (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 39)
    Typescripts (6), photographs (18), publicity, clippings.
  - Stieglitz, Alfred and his photography collection, Undated (Box 21 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 40)
    Typescripts (2), notes, photographs (27), publicity, clippings.
  - Sweet, Ozzie, Undated; Typescript, clippings. (Box 22 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 1)
  - United Nations Photographers, Undated (Box 22 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 2)
    Typescripts (4), photographs (30), publicity, clippings.
  - The invisible made visible. "Once Invisible" exhibit in the Museum of Modern Art, 1967 (Box 22 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 3)
  - Victorian Photography. Exhibit in Metropolitan Museum, 1967 (Box 22 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 4)
  - Vishniak, Roman, Undated (Box 22 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 5)
  - Weegee, Undated (Box 22 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 6)
    See also Box 25, Folder 24.
  - Weiner, Dan, Undated (Box 22 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 7)
  - Weston, Edward, Undated (Box 22 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 8)
    Typescripts (4), photographs (33), clippings.
  - World Exhibitions of Photography, New York, Lucerne, Sport, Undated (Box 22 (7-Photography and Photographers), Folder 9)
- General journalistic articles, 1950s-1979; 8; 49 file folders
  This series consists of typescripts by Neugass, photographs and clippings on general topics, such as world events, cultural events and places.
  - Abu Simbel. Rescue Action by UNESCO, 1963 (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 10)
    Typescript, notes, photographs (5), press releases, clippings.
  - Africa, a Continent in Change, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 11)
    Typescript, notes, press release, clippings.
  - Africa, a Continent in Change, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 12)
    Photographs (80).
  - Alaska, before and after it became the 49th state of the US, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 13)
    Typescripts (2), notes, photographs (24), press releases, clippings.
  - American Museum of Natural History, Hall of North American Forests opening, 1958 May (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 14)
    Typescript, press releases.
  - Animalport. Services for animals at Idlewild airport, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 15)
    Printed clipping of text by Neugass only, no typescript, photograph, clippings.
  - Antarctica, exploration of, including penguin photo by Fritz Neugass, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 16)
    Typescript, notes, photographs (5), clippings.
  - Arthritis, new ways to fight back, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 17)
    Typescript, photographs (14), press releases.
  - Bismarck, Otto, Chef of the liner "S. S. United States", Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 18)
    Typescripts (2), photographs (5), clipping.
  - Canadian school train, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 19)
  - Disneyland. Opening in Anaheim, CA, 1955 Summer (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 20)
    Typescript, photographs (24), press release, clippings.
  - Ford, Henry, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 21)
    Typescripts (3), notes, photographs (39), press releases (1953), clippings.
  - Glass Models of Protozoa, made by Herman Otto Müller, German glassblower, for the American Museum of Natural History, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 22)
  - Guatemala, revolution, 1954 (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 23)
    Typescripts (2), notes, photographs (6), clippings.
  - Hagen, Sylvia von. Expedition of Incan roads in Peru, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 24)
    Typescript, notes, photographs (35), press release, clippings.
  - Hawaii, before and after becoming 50th state of the US, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 25)
    Typescripts (2), notes, photographs (25), press releases, clippings.
  - Highways in the US, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 26)
    Typescript, notes, photographs (4), brochure, clippings.
  - Jack, Hulan Edwin, first black mayor of Manhattan, 1953 (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 27)
    Typescript, notes, photographs (13), press releases.
  - Life Saving courses, American Red Cross, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 28)
    Typescripts (2), photographs (15).
  - Living tableaux. Festival of Arts in Laguna Beach, CA, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 29)
    Typescript, photographs (2), press releases, clippings.
  - Matera, Italy. Rescue action by United Nations, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 30)
    Typescript, photographs (6), clipping.
  - Meyner, Robert, Governor of New Jersey, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 31)
  - Mushrooms with hallucinogenic effect, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 32)
    Typescript, photographs (5), press release, clippings.
  - Neiman-Marcus, Texas, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 33)
    Typescripts (2), photographs (5), press releases, clippings.
  - New York Harbor, Port Authority, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 34)
    Including 2 original photos by Fritz Neugass. Typescript, photographs (23), press releases, clippings.
  - Oil, through the millennia, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 35)
    Typescripts (2), photographs (9), brochures, clipping.
  - Pan American Highway System, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 36)
    Typescript, notes, correspondence, photographs (9), pamphlets, clippings.
  - Pittsburgh, PA Renovation, Undated (Box 22 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 37)
    Typescript, press release.
  - Puerto Rico, Undated (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 1)
    Typescripts (2), press releases, pamphlets, clippings.
  - Quebec, Undated (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 2)
    Typescript, photographs (2), press releases.
  - Radio City Music Hall, Undated (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 3)
  - Roof gardens in New York, Undated (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 4)
    Including 5 original photos by Fritz Neugass. Typescript, photographs (8), clippings.
  - Rubinstein, Helena, Undated (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 5)
    Typescript, photographs (3), press releases.
  - Satellites in Space, 1956 (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 6)
    Typescript, photographs (9), press releases, clippings.
  - Soldiers for Peace, U. N. Troops, Undated (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 7)
    Typescript, notes, photographs (13), clippings.
  - St. Lawrence River Project, Undated (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 8)
    Typescripts (2), notes, photographs (26), pamphlets, press releases, clippings.
  - Supermarkets in miniature, Undated (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 9)
    Typescripts (3), photographs (4), press releases.
  - Tanglewood Music Festivals, Undated (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 10)
    Including 5 original photos by Fritz Neugass. Typescript, photographs (9), press releases.
  - Toys designed for industry, exhibited in Museum of Modern Art, 1953 (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 11)
    Typescripts (2), photographs (2), press release.
  - Treasure Hunters of sunken Spanish ships in Florida; also auction of finds, 1967 (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 12)
    Typescripts (3), correspondence, photographs (6), pamphlet, press releases, clippings.
  - U-boat 505, German submarine, 1944, salvaged by American fleet, Undated (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 13)
    Typescript, photographs (4), press releases.
  - UNESCO Relief work in Central America (Mexico), Undated (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 14)
    Typescript, photographs (15), pamphlets.
  - UNICEF in Greece. Captions by Fritz Neugass, no text, Undated (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 15)
    Photographs (4).
  - Uranium City, Saskatchewan, Canada, Undated (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 16)
  - Venezuela Oil Boom, Undated (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 17)
    Typescript, photographs (5), pamphlets, press releases, clippings.
  - Vinland Map, 1965-1966; 1977; Undated (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 18)
    Typescripts (2), press release, clippings.
  - Volker, William. Volker Memorial Fountain, Kansas City, by Carl Milles, Undated (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 19)
    Typescript, photographs (9), press releases.
  - White House, Washington, D.C. Redecoration by Jacqueline Kennedy, Undated (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 20)
  - Collection of articles, captions by Neugass, Undated (Box 23 (8-General journalistic articles), Folder 21)
    Typescripts (20), clippings.
- Articles with text and photos by Neugass, 1950s-1979; 9; 60 file folders
  This series contains typescripts of articles by Neugass, accompanied by his own original photographs, as well as background materials used for the articles.
  - American Life. Collection of texts (7) on life in America in German and in English, with captions but without photos (preserved separately), Undated (Box 23 (9-Articles with text and photos by ), Folder 22)
  - Amish in Pennsylvania. Texts in German and English, photographs by Neugass (14), clippings, Undated (Box 23 (9-Articles with text and photos by ), Folder 23)
  - Angler Express. Text in German, captions in German and English, photographs by Neugass (13), Undated (Box 23 (9-Articles with text and photos by ), Folder 24)
  - April in Paris Ball. Fashion show by Dior at Waldorf Astoria Hotel, 1958 (Box 23 (9-Articles with text and photos by ), Folder 25)
    Text in German, photographs by Neugass (35), seating chart, clippings.
  - Baumgartner, Dr. Leona, municipal physician of New York. Text in German, photographs by Neugass (3), vita, clippings, Undated (Box 23 (9-Articles with text and photos by ), Folder 26)
  - Beausacq, Ingeborg de. Contact prints, photographs by Fritz Neugass (10), photograph and text by Beausacq in German and in English, no text by Fritz Neugass preserved, possibly never written, Undated (Box 23 (9-Articles with text and photos by ), Folder 27)
  - Berlin Philharmonic, with Herbert von Karajan in New York, 1956 (Box 23 (9-Articles with text and photos by ), Folder 28)
    Text in German, contact prints, photographs by Neugass (35), 6 publicity photos, program.
  - Boys Brotherhood Republic. Text and captions in English and German, letterhead, photographs by Neugass (3), Undated (Box 23 (9-Articles with text and photos by ), Folder 29)
  - Brooklyn Bridge. 75th Anniversary, 1958 (Box 23 (9-Articles with text and photos by ), Folder 30)
    Text and captions in German, photographs by Neugass (8), programs, press release, clippings.
  - Camera Clubs. Text in English, photographs by Neugass (1) and others (8), Undated (Box 23 (9-Articles with text and photos by ), Folder 31)
  - Chewing Gum. Text in German, photographs by Neugass (8), Undated (Box 23 (9-Articles with text and photos by ), Folder 32)
  - Childrens Theater in the US. Performance in Central Park. Text in English and in German, contact prints, photographs by Neugass (29), clipping, Undated (Box 23 (9-Articles with text and photos by ), Folder 33)
  - Chinatown, New York. Text in German, photographs by Neugass (16), clippings, Undated (Box 23 (9-Articles with text and photos by ), Folder 34)
  - Columns, Castles, Minarets, Undated (Box 23 (9-Articles with text and photos by ), Folder 35)
    Draft of a planned book which should have been published in 1946 at Herbert Bittner, text and photos by Fritz Neugass. Versions of the text, list of photographs, captions.